地          球          脉          动
树木是众多生命中的伟大一员
Trees. Surely among the most magnificent of all living things.
有些树是地球上最大的物种， 其他生命在它面前显得相当渺小
Some are the largest organisms on Earth
这些是长得最高的一种树.
dwarfing all others, and these are the tallest of them all.
落叶林和针叶林都生长在 地球上有明显季节变化的地区
The deciduous and coniferous woodlands that grow in the seasonal parts of our planet
在地球上分布最为广泛
are the most extensive forests on Earth.
它们的分布之广，超出想象
Their sheer extent stuns the imagination.
季           节           森           林
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
冰雪覆盖的北极地区
The barren snows of the Arctic.
这是距离北极点以南1000英里的地方
A thousand miles from the North Pole, and heading south.
这也是树木长到的最北处
This is the very first place that trees can grow.
一开始松树比较稀疏
To begin with the conifers are sparse
再往南它们便马上支配了大陆
but soon they dominate the land.
这就是泰加针叶林
This is the Taiga Forest.
它的面积，是所有热带雨林面积的总和
There are as many trees here, as in all the world's rainforests combined.
针叶林环球分布 占全球所有树木总量的三分之一
The Taiga circles the globe and contains a third of all the trees on Earth.
它制造了大量的氧气 是我们这个地球的空气清新剂
It produces so much oxygen, that it refreshes the atmosphere of the entire planet.
在针叶林的北部区域 树木的一年内的生长时节只有1个月
At the Taiga's northern extent the growing season can last for just one month a year.
一棵树从秧苗到成年需要50年的时间
It can take fifty years for a tree to get bigger than a seedling.
除了偶有动静，这里万籁俱寂
It's a silent world where little stirs
即使在满是冰雪的童话世界中
But there are occasional signs of life.
也有非常特别的生命
Stories written in the snow.
北极狐追捕野兔的脚印
The prints of an Arctic fox and the hare it might've been stalking.
这是雌性北极熊
A female polar bear
和她的2个孩子的脚印
and her two cubs.
有些动物如幽灵般
Some animals are so difficult to glimpse
难得一见
that they're like spirits.
你可能在森林里呆一辈子
One could live a lifetime in these woods
也不会见到一只猞猁
and never see a lynx.
这只猫(猞猁属于猫科的一种) 为寻找猎物跋涉了几百英里
The cat must roam hundreds of miles in search of prey
而且树林中同一地方它可能不会来第二次
and may never visit the same patch of forest twice.
这是在原始森林中生存的基本
It's the very essence of wilderness.
猎物是如此至少，捕猎对于它们来说是极端困难
With so few prey animals here, life for a hunter is particularly hard.
这里缺乏生物的原因是很少有生物以针叶为食
Creatures are scarce because few can eat conifer needles.
北美驼鹿是个例外
The moose is an exception.
因为生长困难 针叶树木用树脂来保护宝贵的叶子
Growth is so difficult that conifers protect their precious leaves by filling them with resin.
以减少水分流失 这样也让针叶变得难以食用
That reduces water loss, but it also makes them very distasteful.
至少松果是可以食用的
At least the conifer's seeds are edible
但松果被层层装甲包围着
but they're protected within armor plated cones
还是有破甲专家可以吃到
and it takes a specialist to reach them.
交喙鸟用非常特别的喙分开松果的鳞片
The crossbill's extraordinary beak can prise apart the scales,
然后用舌头来卷取种子
so that it's tongue can extract the seeds.
鸟类是幸福的 当收获季节结束时，它们可以向南方飞去
Birds are fortunate. When the seasonal crop is gathered, they can fly south
不过有一种动物是在这个冰雪森林中生存的专家
But one animal is so expert at survival in this frozen forest
所以它可以终生在这里活动
that it stays here and is active all year long.
当地传说狼獾 是人跟灵界的连系而且是狼跟熊的混血儿
In local folklore, the wolverine is a link to the spirit world and a cross between a bear and a wolf.
实际上，它不过是最大的鼬科动物罢了
In reality, it's a huge weasel.
它的体型有利于 帮助保持体内热量和扩充食物来源
It's bulk helps to conserve body heat and also broadens it's menu.
它大而强壮，甚至可以干掉一头成年北美驯鹿
It's so big and powerful, it can even bring down an adult caribou.
据说它每一餐的食量是同体型动物的一倍半
For it's size, it's said that the animal can eat more in one sitting than any other
可以被认为是暴食型动物
which is why it's also known as the glutton.
在这种环境下，暴食不失为一种有效策略
Being gluttonous here is a very effective strategy.
能吃多少就吃多少
It's wise to eat all you can, when you can
当吃不下的时候 就把食物储存起来，以应付酷寒的到来
and when even a glutton can't eat more it stores what's left for later, in the surrounding deep freeze.
冰雪森林的春天
Spring in the ice forest.
北欧雷鸟也吃针叶林的针叶
The capercaillie can also digest conifer needles
不过此时它还没有享用的优先权
but feeding is not it's priority at the moment.
如同角斗士，雄鸡们为战斗摆好了架势
Like gladiators, the males square up for a battle.
只有一个机会来取得雌鸟的芳心
Each may have just a single chance to impress a female.
必须全神贯注，不能失败
Neither can afford a lapse in concentration.
受伤的雷鸟不会活下来
The injured loser may not survive.
这片广阔森林的居民们
The inhabitants of this great wilderness
可以不受人类干扰，自由生存和死亡
may live and die without ever having contact with humanity.
希望永远如此
Long may it be that way.
地球北部的森林可能地球上最大的森林了
The northern forest may be the largest on Earth
不过想要一览针叶林的全貌, 你要还要再向南走1000英里
but to see coniferous trees that have reached their full potential you must travel a thousand miles south of here.
北美洲，太平洋沿岸
The Pacific Coast of North America.
铁杉，花旗松,巨杉
The land of hemlock, douglas fir and giant redwood.
这里，水再也不会冰封
Here, water is never locked up in ice
即使不下雨, 针叶也可以从海上蜂拥而来的水雾中汲取水分
and even if rains fail the needles can extract moisture from the fogs that roll in from the sea.
太阳给森林带来的生长能量
The Sun's energy powers these forests
不是北极的一个月，而是半年
not for one month as it does in the Taiga but for half the year.
这些树木的生长速度是北极圈附近树木的10倍
These conifers grow at ten times the rate of those near the Arctic
寿命更可达数千年
and they live for thousands of years.
加利福尼亚的这块红杉林
One grove of redwoods in California
世界树木高度排行前三名的树都在这里
contains three of the tallest trees on Earth.
这颗超过100米的树有30层楼房那么高
This one is over a hundred meters high, the size of a thirty story building.
这片森林远在人类直立行走之前就出现了
These forests were growing here long before humans walked the Earth.
2000万年前它们就已经在这里
They were in their prime twenty million years ago
甚至比阿尔卑斯山(欧洲) 和洛基山脉(美洲最长的山脉)隆起的时间还要早
and existed before the Swiss Alps or the Rocky Mountains were even raised.
比起热带雨林来
There is more living matter in a forest of giant conifers,
巨大针叶林里的有机物质要多的多 但是都在大树里
than in any tropical rainforest but it's all contained within the trees.
针叶依然如北极针叶林那样难吃 所以动物仍然稀少
These are as inedible as those in the Taiga so animals are still scarce,
还是有意外的惊喜
but they are present.
松貂
A pine marten.
春天，是松貂找食的最佳时节
It's spring, the best time of year for a marten to find food.
鸟卵是季节性的美餐 虽然数量众多,只是不能长时间享受
Bird's eggs are a seasonal snack and for a short time, there's plenty of them
有时候可能是…太多了
Sometimes perhaps, too many.
要在这里常住，松貂就需要稳定的食物来源
But to live here permanently, the marten needs a more reliable food source.
松鼠就是
Squirrels fit the bill.
松鼠以松果为食, 虽然松果是季节性生长的
They thrive here on the pine cones and although these are also seasonal
但可以贮藏起来吃一整年
they can be stored and eaten throughout the year.
松鼠忙着交配
The squirrels are busy mating
这是猎人的好消息 心烦意乱的松鼠，就十分容易被抓住了
Good news for the hunter. A distracted squirrel, is a vulnerable squirrel.
不过，这对情意绵绵的情侣十分安全
But, this time, the amorous couple is safe.
有一只正在他的储藏室里美餐的松鼠 是更容易捕捉的目标
There is a loner stocking his larder, who will be the easier target.
早夏，乌林鸮的孩子刚刚长大
Early summer, and great grey owl chicks are fledging.
成鸟能在这里养育小宝宝 表示今年的田鼠够多可以养活它们
Adults can only raise young here in years when the seasonal vole crop is big enough to support them.
小乌林鸮的第一次飞行时间到了
The moment has arrived for their first flight.
要从世界上最高的树木上跳下，可不能恐高
Leaping from the world's tallest trees is not for the faint hearted.
想要从这里落下，分阶段进行不失为一种好方法
If you're going to fall here it's quite a good idea to do it in stages.
地面对乌林鸮来说只是个落脚点
The ground is no place for an owl.
想要在班上名列前矛，必须有毅力
If he's to climb to the top of his class he'll need to persevere
现在，可以再来一次了
So now, let's have another go.
美洲的针叶林
The American conifer forests
可能不是动物的乐园
may not be the richest in animal life
但这些树木非常特别
but their trees are extraordinary.
这些美洲杉是红杉的亲戚,也是世界上最大的生物
This giant sequoia, a relative of the redwood, is the largest living thing on Earth.
谢尔曼将军树有十头蓝鲸那么重
Known as General Sherman, it's the weight of ten blue whales.
附近的高山上，狐尾松 是地球上最长寿的生物
Higher up in the nearby mountains, bristlecone pines, the oldest organisms on the planet.
有的在这里已经待了5000年
Some have been here for five thousand years.
它们在金字塔建造之前就发芽了， 耶稣诞生的时候它们已经活了3000年
They were alive before the pyramids were built and were already three thousand years old when Christ was born.
穿越赤道来到南半球 这里的森林如同北半球的翻版
Across the Equator, in the southern hemisphere there are forests that mirror those of the north.
这是南美洲, 绰号叫“猴子谜”的南洋杉看上去和极地针叶林没什么两样
Here in South America araucaria trees or monkey puzzles are like the conifers of the Taiga.
它们用防水的鳞片代替了针叶 球果也有些不同
They have waterproof scales, instead of needles and their cones look a little different
不过它们在本质上还是一样的
but the principles are the same.
尖嘴锥尾鹦鹉和交喙鸟来一样啄出种籽取食
Slender billed parakeets rather than crossbills, extract their seeds.
由于更长的生长季节, 南半球也有红杉-智利柏树
Where the growing season is longerm, there are alerce trees the redwoods of the south.
难道如同寒冷的北极, 巴尔第毕亚温带森林只有很少的动物?
As in the frozen north, the Valdivian forests of Chile support very few animals
这种相似性在这里是不存在的
but that is the end of the similarity.
这里是小动物的奇异世界
This is a bizarre world of miniature creatures.
智利普度鹿 世界上最小的鹿之一，正在吃根乃拉草的大叶子
The pudu, the world's smallest deer feeds on the giant leaves of the gunnera plant.
雌鹿肩高仅仅30厘米高
The female is just thirty centimeters high at the shoulder
她的孩子不比小猫大多少
and her infants are hardly bigger than kittens.
妈妈必须保持警惕，猎人正在觑觎着孩子
The male must stay alert. There are hunters here who would snatch his young.
另一种小动物--南美林猫
Another miniature. The kodkod cat.
对于这种美洲最小的猫科动物来说 小普度鹿无疑是它的美餐
It's the smallest cat in all the Americas and a young pudu would be a feast for it
由于母鹿在警戒着，南美林猫只好放弃
But, with the male on guard, the kodkod must lower his sights.
飞蛾正在孵化
Moths are hatching.
今年夏天最后一批, 小猫应该可以抓到它们
They're the last of the summer. The tiny cat should be able to score with these.
没人知道为什么这里的动物这么小
No one knows why the creatures here are so small
至少它们可以在这个贫瘠的地方存活
but at least they can survive on meager rations.
你可以称这个游戏为:猫抓飞蛾
You might call this a game of cat and moth.
冬季逼近智利
As winter approaches in Chile
北半球的春天却来了
spring is arriving in the northern hemisphere.
这是我家乡的落叶林
These are the deciduous forests of Homme.
从冬天苏醒后，它们开始了自然界最神奇的转变
Dormant throughout the winter, they now undergo one of the most magical transformations in the natural world.
到了晚春，大地一片翠绿,风景如画
By late spring the landscape is wrapped in a vibrant fresh green.
阔叶林代替针叶林
Here, instead of conifers, there are broad leaved trees
同时也展现了完全不同的世界
and that makes the character of this forest entirely different.
不仅叶子能比针叶吸收更多阳光
Being broad, these leaves trap much more light than needles
而且叶子更薄，更软，更好吃
but they're also thin, soft and edible.
螳螂捕蝉，黄雀在后
And others can eat the leaf eaters.
这是跨越东欧-亚洲-俄罗斯的 世界上最大的落叶阔叶林的春天
It's spring in the great broad leaved forests of Eastern Europe and Asiatic Russia.
鸳鸯正在示爱
The mandarin ducks are courting.
雌鸳鸯在树上筑巢
The female mandarin nests in a tree hole
她正在带着所有的宝宝们离开巢穴
and when it's time for everyone to leave she leads the way.
小鸳鸯才24个小时大
The ducklings are only twenty four hours old.
要让它们从这么高的地方落下 妈妈鼓励的叫声是必须的
It's a long drop, and a few calls of encouragement are required.
2只降落，还有7只
Two down seven to go.
还少着2只
There are still two missing.
如数到齐
All present and correct.
在赶到水中之前它们还很不安全
But they won't be safe until they reach water
林中的池塘还有1英里远呢
and the forest pool is almost a mile away.
6月是白昼最长的时候
By June the days are at their longest
所有北半球的阔叶树木努力生长
and all across the northern hemisphere the broad leaves are hard at work.
在北美洲的东部
On the east coast of North America
这里的夏日傍晚和其他地方一样
it seems like any other summer's evening
不过今晚非常特别
but tonight is special.
在17年的地下潜伏后
After seventeen years underground
一种生物开始活跃起来
creatures are stirring.
布鲁德蝉(一种周期蝉)的幼虫 为这个机会等待了很长时间
The nymphs of the periodical cicada have been biding their time.
现在它们如朝圣般向最近的树进军 并开始攀爬
Now they march like zombies towards the nearest tree, and start to climb.
一开始，不过几千只
At first, there are merely thousands
马上，10亿只幼虫爬满了整个森林
but soon, more than a billion swarm all over the forest.
地球上最大规模的昆虫羽化就要开始了
The biggest insect emergence on the planet is underway.
占据上端的树枝后 幼虫开始进行转变到蝉的蜕皮动作
They invade the upper branches, where they climb out of their external skeletons and assume their adult winged form.
一开始它们又白又软
At first they're white and soft,
直到黎明它们才完全转化完毕
but they have until dawn to complete their transformation.
在17年的缺席之后 森林中的蝉泛滥成灾
After an absence of seventeen years, the forest is now overrun by cicadas.
成年蝉不仅笨拙而且非常美味
The adults are clumsy and very edible.
对于龟和其他森林居民来说, 可能再也没有运气能这样狼吞虎咽
For turtles and other inhabitants of the forest this is a feast they're lucky to see once in their lifetime
大快朵颐
and they gorge themselves while they can.
美好时光！
Times have never been so good.
蝉毫无防卫而且好像是 把自己送上门供享用
The cicadas have no defenses and virtually offer themselves to their attackers.
这种昆虫川流不息的出现
The stream of insects is so relentless
使得捕食者数量很快就暴涨
that soon all the predators are full to the point of bursting
仍然有大量的蝉赶来
and still the cicadas come.
当捕食者达到饱和，存活的蝉也在完成它们的使命
With the predators overwhelmed the survivors can achieve their purpose.
成蝉在交配完并产卵后，它们的工作也完成了
After mating, the adults lay their eggs and then their job is done.
几天的时间内他们全将死去，森林又会恢复平静
In just a few days they will all die and the forest will fall silent.
在接下来的17年里，不会再听到布鲁德蝉的声音了
The cicadas here, will not be heard again for another seventeen years.
喂饱了掠食者后，蝉给森林留下了最后的礼物
Having fed the predators, the cicadas leave one final gift for the forest itself.
这些蝉给土壤提供了大量养分
The nutrients in a generation of cicadas are returned to the soil, all at once
树木也可以享受疯长的乐趣
and the trees enjoy a marked spurt in growth.
这可能是自然界最大剂量的一支营养针
This may be the single largest dose of fertilizer in the natural world.
在东欧的大片落叶阔叶林那边
In the great broad leaf forests of Eastern Europe
白昼开始缩短
the days are beginning to shorten,
一声富有攻击力的原始声音在宣布秋天的到来
and a primeval sound heralds the onset of autumn.
雄性马鹿正在按惯例行事
Male red deer are starting their rut.
空气中弥漫着雌马鹿的气味
The air is heavy with the scent of females.
规则很简单
The rules are simple.
胜利者取得一切
Winner takes all.
环绕整个北半球
Across the northern hemisphere
可以看到落叶林在不断变化
the deciduous forests are changing.
从春天开始提供给动物食物和掩护的树叶 开始脱落了
Leaves that have provided food and shelter since the spring, are now shed.
在俄罗斯的阔叶林中
In the broad leaf forests of Russia
冬天是特别严酷
winter is particularly severe
但总是有一些动物从中获益
but there will always be some who benefit from hardship.
黑秃鹫寻找死去和饿死的鹿，以它们的腐肉为食
Black vultures scavenge from the carcass of a seeker deer that has died of cold or starvation.
这些濒临灭绝的鸟儿从更加寒冷的西伯利亚来访
These endangered birds are visitors. They've come down from the north to escape the even colder conditions in Siberia.
一只远东豹.
An Amur leopard.
世界上最稀少的猫科动物
The rarest cat on Earth.
冬天对这个动物来说相当难熬
Winter is a difficult time for this hunter.
没有树叶可以掩护，没有幼小的猎物
There are no leaves for cover and no young prey animals.
这只雌豹因为要抚养她的一岁大的孩子 而担负着更大的压力
This female has the added pressure, of having to provide for her one year old cub.
还得再过一年，小豹才能照顾自己
It'll be another twelve months, before he'll be able to fend for himself.
秃鹫的叫声说明它们放弃了那块畜体
The bickering vultures have abandoned the carcass.
对于豹子来说这是重要的发现
It's a valuable discovery for the leopards.
小豹却不知道她妈妈着急的心情
But the cub doesn't share it's mother's sense of urgency.
秃鹫虽然留下了这块上好的肉
The vultures have left behind plenty of good meat
不过这块肉冻得太硬了
but it's stiff with frost.
母豹撕开兽皮，好让她的小豹吃起来容易点
The mother works to open the hide, and make feeding a little easier for her cub.
目前仅有40只左右的远东豹
There are only forty Amur leopards left in the wild
而且它的数量还在减少
and that number is still falling.
严酷的冬天阻碍了这个种群数量的增长
The harshness of the winter here hinders their increasing numbers.
比起非洲豹来 母豹养大她的孩子成人所花的时间要长很多
It takes one of these females longer to raise her young to independence than it does a leopard in Africa.
如果母豹能和小豹多坚持几个星期
If the mother can sustain her cub for a few more weeks
等到春天随着食物的回升 母豹的任务也会变得轻松一些
spring will bring an increase in prey and her task will lighten.
对于这个季相林的所有居民来说
For all the inhabitants of this seasonal forest
漫长寒冷的冬天即将过去
the long, cold wait is nearly over.
春天的落叶林是很特别的
Spring in a deciduous woodland is special.
由于没有树叶遮蔽，阳光可以直射到森林地表上
With no leaves overhead, the rays of the sun strike the forest floor directly
这种温暖让植物们从冬眠中苏醒过来
and their warmth rouses plants from their winter sleep.
地表植物正在匆忙生长, 不久之后,树木长出的新叶将会重新把阳光夺去
The ground living plants are in a hurry. Before long the trees above will come into leaf and steal their light.
花，是森林地表的天然装饰 它们以花蜜为广告，来吸引新生的昆虫
Their flowers decorate the forest floor as they advertise their sweet nectar to the newly emerged insects.
春天使得落叶林与针叶林和雨林
The spring blooms of the deciduous woodlands have no equivalent in either the great conifer forests,
没有任何相似性
or the tropical jungles.
再过几个星期，树冠层重新遮蔽天空, 透到地面的只有丝丝缕缕的阳光
Within a matter of weeks the canopy has closed and only a few wheeling shafts of light penetrate the woodland.
在树梢 树叶很快生长开来并保持这个状态一直到夏末
In the treetops, the broad leaves rapidly expand to their full size to make the most of summer while it lasts.
几个月后，白昼又开始缩短
Then, after a few months, the days begin to shorten again
树木开始减缓代谢，树叶开始凋零, 以准备迎接寒冬的到来
and the trees must shut down and shed their leaves in preparation for the cold dark time ahead.
随着季节的变换 北美的大片地域万山红遍,层林尽染
Great tracts of North America flush red as the season progresses.
这种壮观的景象发生的地域之广
The effect is so spectacular and so extensive
甚至可以在太空中看到
that it can be seen from space.
寒冬的威胁不是树木落叶的唯一原因
The threat of winter frost is not the only reason for trees to shed leaves.
这片森林在热带地区
These forests stand in the tropics.
在这里白昼没有变化
Here day length never changes
在炎热干燥的季节
but the dry season is so severe
树木无法承受水分从叶子上的大量流失
that the trees can't afford to loose the amount of water that would evaporate from their broad leaves,
所以，必须落叶
so the leaves must be shed.
这片森林看上去和冬季欧洲的森林相似
The forest resembles a European woodland in mid winter
但是这里的酷热让人无法承受，动物也不为人熟悉
but the heat is overpowering, and it's inhabitants, unfamiliar.
对于印度的这个柚木林的动物们来说
For the creatures of India's teak forests,
这是让人绝望的时刻
these are desperate times
不过救命稻草就在附近
but salvation is at hand.
山榄正在开花
The mahwa tree is about to bloom.
多汁的花让动物们疯狂
It's flowers are full of liquid making them irresistible.
山榄对于它们来讲就是沙漠中的绿洲
The mahwa is an oasis in a hot dry desert.
这些花也不是只给会飞的和会爬树的享用
Those that fly or climb are not the only ones to get a share.
白斑鹿跟随着长尾叶猴，收集掉下的花
Chital deer follow the langur monkeys collecting the flowers that fall.
叶猴对白斑鹿的到来表示欢迎, 因为鹿可以帮助侦察掠食者
The monkeys welcome the deer, for deer are unrivaled at spotting predators.
如果白斑鹿显得无拘无束 那么叶猴可以安心从地面上采集食物
If they are relaxed, it must be safe to come down to the ground and gather the food that lies there
不过远离哨兵是不明智的
but it's not wise to travel far from the sentinels.
马达加斯加岛(非洲)的热带地区 雨季
Tropical Madagascar. The wet season.
现在波巴布树长出了新叶
It's now that the baobab trees regrow their leaves
用来收集水分并储存到巨大的躯干中 用以对付旱季的到来
and collect water to store in their huge trunks, ready for the dry season ahead.
波巴布树的外形已经相当被人们熟悉了
The prehistoric shape of these trees is rightly famous
但是很少有人能看到波巴布树的真正魔力
but few have ever witnessed the baobab's real magic
这发生在夜晚，波巴布树的树顶
for that happens at night and high in the treetops.
在水的作用下 波巴布树正在准备一场让人终生难忘的演出
Flush with water, the baobab prepares itself for an unforgettable display.
长长的花可以在1分钟之内完全展开…
Once started the foot long flowers can open fully in less than a minute.
当花开的时候，动物们也被唤醒了
As the flowers open, the creatures of the forest wake.
鼠狐猴从旱季的冬眠中醒来
The mouse lemurs have been hibernating throughout the dry season.
雨季来临时，它们就开始忙碌了
With the return of rains it's time to get busy.
12只鼠狐猴同居此洞 对于这种巴掌大小 世界上最小的灵长动物来说，空间足够了
A dozen share this tree hole, but there's plenty of room. The world's smallest primate is no bigger than your hand.
高处的波巴布树已经开始分泌花蜜了
High in the branches above, the baobab's nectar is starting to flow.
饮用这些高糖高能的花蜜
A drink of this sugary energy packed liquid
对狐猴来讲是美好一天的开始
is an ideal way for the lemurs to start their day.
花蜜从花中央渗出 流到花瓣上
Liquid oozes from the flower's center and trickles down the petals
不过花蜜不是只留给狐猴的
But the nectar is not intended for lemurs.
这些大天蛾才是树木想要吸引的
These giant hawk moths are the drinkers the tree needs to attract.
当它们在树与树之间采蜜的时候 也给树完成了传精授粉
As they sip, moving from tree to tree, so they transfer pollen and fertilize the flowers.
花蜜是鼠狐猴的美妙的饭前点心
Nectar was an excellent first course for the lemurs
飞蛾才是正餐
but moths are the main dish.
飞蛾对狐猴相当重要
The moths are very important to the lemurs
飞蛾是狐猴挺过旱季的重要的脂肪来源
for they will replenish the fat reserves that the lemurs need to survive the barren dry season.
鼠狐猴好像对波巴布树来说是害虫
The lemurs might seem to be a pest for the baobab.
它们杀死授粉者又抢夺花蜜, 不过鼠狐猴的确对树木有所回报
They kill it's pollinators and rob it of it's nectar but they do give something in return.
因为，当狐猴捕捉飞蛾的时候, 它们的毛皮不可避免的会沾上花粉
For, as the wrestle with the moths, their fur inevitably becomes dusted with pollen
所以，它们也成了授粉者
so they, too, become pollinators.
旱季雨季的交替变换给热带的树木带来了变化
As the alternation of wet and dry seasons brings change to some tropical forests
从夏季到冬季的变换 也决定了温带地区的生物物种
so the progression of summer to winter dictates life in more temperate regions.
不管树木是针叶还是阔叶
Whether trees have needles or broad leaves
它们这种在季节变化生存的本领
it is their ability to survive annual change, that has enabled them to cover
使得季相林覆盖了地球上大片的地方
such vast areas of the Earth
也使季相林变得最为伟大
and made the seasonal forests the greatest forests of all.